<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation, of the most chiefe occurrences, at, and since the late battell at Newbery, untill the disjunction of the three armies, of the Lord Generall, the Earle of Manchester, and Sir William Waller, together with the London brigade, under the command of Sir Iames Harrington. Published upon necessity, both to undeceive the mistaken multitude, and to vindicate the Earle of Manchester, from many undeserved aspersions commonly cast upon him, either through ignorance or prejudice. / Penned by Simeon Ash, who as his chaplaine did waite upon his Lordship, in the westerne expedition.</title>
            <author>Ashe, Simeon, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E22_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871460</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123871</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75714)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123871)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 4:E22[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation, of the most chiefe occurrences, at, and since the late battell at Newbery, untill the disjunction of the three armies, of the Lord Generall, the Earle of Manchester, and Sir William Waller, together with the London brigade, under the command of Sir Iames Harrington. Published upon necessity, both to undeceive the mistaken multitude, and to vindicate the Earle of Manchester, from many undeserved aspersions commonly cast upon him, either through ignorance or prejudice. / Penned by Simeon Ash, who as his chaplaine did waite upon his Lordship, in the westerne expedition.</title>
                  <author>Ashe, Simeon, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for Edward Brewster at the signe of the Bible at Fleete-Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIV. [1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 24.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harrington, James, 1611-1677.</term>
               <term>Manchester, Edward Montagu, --  Earl of, 1602-1671.</term>
               <term>Waller, William, --  Sir, 1597?-1668.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123871:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION, OF THE MOST Chiefe Occurrences, at, and ſince the late Battell at <hi>Newbery,</hi> untill the disjunction of the three Armies, of the Lord Generall, the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> together with the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Brigade, under the Command of Sir <hi>Iames Harrington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed upon neceſſity, both to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive the miſtaken multitude, and to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Earle of <hi>MANCHESTER,</hi> From many undeſerved aſperſions commonly caſt upon him, either through ignorance or prejudice.</p>
            <p>Penned by SIMEON ASH, Who as his Chaplaine did waite upon his Lordſhip, in the Weſterne Expedition.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 18, 17.</hi>
               </bibl> He that is first in his own cauſe, ſeemeth juſt, but his neighbour commeth and ſearcheth him.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 19.21.</hi>
               </bibl> There are many devicees in the heart of a man, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, the counſell of the Lord, that ſhall ſtand.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Edward Brewſter</hi> at the Signe of the Bible at Fleete-Bridge, M.DC.XLIV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:123871:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123871:2"/>
            <head>A true Relation of the moſt chiefe Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, at, and ſince the late Battell at <hi>Newbery,</hi> untill the disjunction of the three Armies of the Lord Generall, the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot only importunity from friends, but neceſſity in regard of others of various wayes and ſpirits, doth compell me to give in a true Narrative according to my knowledge and beſt intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, concerning the proceedings of the three Armies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned (<hi>vid.</hi> the Lord Generals, my Lord of <hi>Mancheſters,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi>) both when the Battell was fought at <hi>Newbery,</hi> and ſince the Enemies retreat from thence. For not only the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of many, but alſo a Letter ſent unto me, doe ſuggeſt; that my ſilence, now, when my teſtimony may doe good ſervice, doth give occaſion both to my No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lords foes and friends, to ſuſpect his faultineſſe (if not unfaithfullneſſe) in a great meaſure; becauſe heretofore I openly appeared in relating his actions in the North, when there was no need to vindicate his reputation; but now I am mute, when his fidelity to Church and Common-wealth is queſtioned, and when he is cenſured, yea clamoured againſt, as the only blame-worthy cauſe of the diſappointments lately in the Weſt. For my ſilence hitherto, I can make this juſt apologie. 1. In regard of the daily intelligence, which went from the Army to <hi>London,</hi> either by Poſt or otherwiſe, I conceived it not neceſſary, or much uſefull for me to be a weekely Intelligencer to my friends in the City, as when the Army lay before <hi>York.</hi> 2. Neither was I altogether ſilent, when I eſpied occaſion and a call to ſpeake: For within few dayes after the releeving of <hi>Dennington</hi> Caſtle, when I underſtood what clamours and cenſures were in <hi>London,</hi> through the miſreport and miſtake of our actions, I gave a ſhort and true Relation of our Occurrences, for the ſatisfaction of private friends, which Relation, was the ſumme of that which I ſhall now report: and at that time I was very farre from imagining, that my Lord, the Earle of <hi>Manchester,</hi> would by any Officer of the Army, be accuſed, as leſſe faithfull, or leſſe carefull then others, in promoting the Kingdomes good. 3. Since the Accuſation charged upon my Lord, in the Honourable Houſe of Commons, I have held my tongue, leſt I ſhould incurre diſpleaſure, by ſeeming pragmaticall, in intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a buſineſſe, committed by them to examination, with expectation of a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123871:3"/>report. But now hearing, that the buſineſſe there is ſuſpended (ſome ſay ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced) and knowing that the lowd cryes of people, either ignorant, or diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to my Lords credit, doe ſound farre and neare, to his diſhonour, I have reſorved to take the boldneſſe, to repreſent what I know, both to vindicate my Noble Lords honour, and to undeceive them (if my teſtimony may be of any credit) who are too apt and eaſie to beleeve calumnies caſt upon well-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving men, wanting patience to waite for truths diſcovery, by a full and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall triall; which in this buſineſſe, cannot be more earneſtly deſired by any: then it is by my Lord himſelfe, and by his beſt friends.</p>
            <p>I wiſh that theſe things may be premiſed, which I ſuppoſe cannot with any colour of truth be contradicted. 1. That no motion, no march, no ſervice of the three Armies after their firſt conjunction, was made or undertaken, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the reluſt of the Councell of Warre. 2. That the Earle of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> never aſſumed to himſelfe, to be accounted or obſerved, as Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chiefe, but alwayes voted, as one that had but equall authority with the reſt, and acted accordingly in obſervation of the orders, concluded by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councell. 3. That he often profeſſed unto the chiefe Commanders; that becauſe himſelfe was no experienced Souldier, therefore he would rather be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, then guide; rather be acted by their counſels, then act on either himſelfe or them, according to his own private thoughts.</p>
            <p>Upon Friday <hi>Octob.</hi> 25. we hoped (from the newes brought in by our Scouts) the day following, to fight with the Enemy; but the next morning drawing up our whole body, we found that the Enemies had in ſuch ſort blockt up the way to <hi>Newbery</hi> by many works, that our hopes of engageing with them were diſappointed. Hereupon it was reſolved at a Councell of Warre, that to force the Enemy to fight, our Forces ſhould in this manner be divided, <hi>(vid.)</hi> All my Lord Generals Horſe and Foote, the greateſt part of my Lord of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> Horſe, and almoſt all the Forces under the Command of Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Heiſlerig,</hi> together with the <hi>London</hi> Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade, did march to <hi>Speene</hi> hill: But the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter;</hi> Foot, with a ſmall body of Horſe, was left in the field on this ſide <hi>Shaw</hi> (a little village) neare to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Dolmans</hi> houſe, which was poſſeſſed and fortified by the Enemy. When the Army was thus divided, this order was left with my Lord of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter;</hi> that ſo ſoone as he heard of the engagement of our Friends on <hi>Spcene</hi> hill (by the diſcharging of the Canon) he ſhould fall on the Enemy on this ſide the River, that he might divert the ſtrength of the battell, from them there.</p>
            <p>I will forbeare here, to relate the hardſhip which both parts of our Army met with, that night; becauſe that would be a digreſſion not to my purpoſe.</p>
            <p>On Sabbath day morning early, my Lord of <hi>Manchester,</hi> with the Forces remaining under his command, were in readineſſe to aſſault the Enemy, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123871:3"/>from hower to hower, to heare of the engagement at <hi>Speene</hi> hill: And here to witneſſe the Earle of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> willingneſſe to fight with the Enemy, let this be noted, which is a known truth <hi>(vid.)</hi> that in the morning, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a party of about 400 Musketeeres to fall on, over the little River, on the left hand of <hi>Shaw,</hi> that he might ſoon enough divert the enemies ſtrength from <hi>Speene</hi> hill: This party of ours, tooke two of the Enemies workes, one Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and ſeverall priſoners; but marching too farre, contrary to order, they were beaten back with ſome loſſe; by this ſervice, the greateſt part of the Kings Foot was drawne towards us, and ſo the worke to which we were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, was accompliſhed long before our friends on <hi>Speene</hi> hill did engage. In this place, I might take occaſion truly to report, the great paines which my Lord <hi>Mancheſter</hi> tooke from morning till evening, often expoſing himſelfe to very much danger (the Enemies Drakes playing frequently upon us) in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from Regiment to Regiment, to encourage the Souldiers, and to keep them in due order, fit for that ſervice which every moment almoſt was expected: but there are many hundreds, I might ſay, divers thouſands, who can tell the truth hereof, which proves, that my Lord was not ſo backward to fight, and ſo regardleſſe of the Kingdomes ſervice that day, as many would have the world to believe. About 4 a clock (as was gueſſed) we heard the Canon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to play on <hi>Speene</hi> hill, at which time, my Lord commanded 2 Drakes to be drawne forth (though our Canon hitherto had not beene altogether idle) and to be planted in a convenient place to doe ſervice againſt the Enemy at <hi>Dolmans</hi> houſe, and to make way for the falling on of our Foot there, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order given, when our Army divided. Thoſe Drakes did good exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution upon the Enemy divers times, forcing their retreat to their works about the houſe. Now we ſaw the fieting of the Muskitieres on <hi>Speene</hi> hill, which diſcovered the ſervice there to be very hot; and not long after, with joy and thankfulneſſe, we beheld the haſty, diſorderly retreat of the Enemy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Newbery,</hi> wondering that our party did not purſue the victory. It is beſides my intention in this Relation, to report the poſture of our Army on <hi>Speene</hi> hill, or to give by a full report, the due praiſe to my Lord Generals Foot and others, who then and there, did excellent and praiſeworthy ſervice: Neither indeed, need I, to beſtow words hereon, becauſe the world hath been acquainted with theſe things heretofore. But my Lord of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> Horſe, commanded by Liev. Col. <hi>Cromwell</hi> (from whom very much was expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) did little ſervice, gained no honour in this worke this day. For my part, I know not whom to blame, I will aſperſe no man, but leave it to their judgement, who were on the ground, to judge who were blame-worthy, in being backward to purſue that happy opportunity, upon the flying, fainting Enemy. Notwithſtanding, let me here tell you, what many ſpeake; That it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123871:4"/>my Lord of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> had now been in his own perſon, at the Head of his body of Horſe, this neglect would have been charged home upon him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions would hence, confidently and clamorouſly have been inferred, that my Lord of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> was unwilling to bring the Kings Army too low, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, now the woefull waſting warres, might in all probability have been ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well ended.</p>
            <p>But to return unto my work. You muſt not imagine that my Lord of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesters</hi> Foot were all this while idle ſpectators on this ſide the River (although as I told you before, the Enemies beſt Foot were diverted from <hi>Speen</hi> hill, which might have extenuated the ſeeming fault of ſome delayes) for while our Drakes (before mentiond) were at work, a commanded party of 500 Muskiteers was drawn forth as a Forelorn-hope, to aſſault the Enemy, who being ſeconded with the ſeveral Brigades of Foot, continued in hot ſervice, until for want of day light to direct, our Souldiers wounded &amp; killed one another. The undaunted va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of our Foot was admirable, they were indeed too forward too adventurous, overrunning their commands, unwilling to be called off. And here this is nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that when one company of our Foot had taken one of the Works of the Enemy, another Company (through overmuch forwardneſſe and miſtake) did beat them out againe. So that our greateſt loſſe, both in regard of men wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſlaine, was from our ſelves. All this while, my Lord of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> was with his Souldiers, (as mine eyes, and thouſands more can witneſſe) to countenance and encourage the ſervice: and thoſe who know what dangers he then adventured upon, and how long he continued in the field that night, yea, what care he took to prevent the miſchiefs of the night from a Neighbour Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and to prepare for the continuance of the battell, which was verily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by us the next morning; thoſe many (I ſay) who underſtood and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber theſe things, will not eaſily believe that his Lordſhip was averſe to fighting, and unwilling ſpeedily to end theſe warres, though multitudes, through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, raſhneſſe, and misbeliefe, do in this manner aſperſe and calumniate him.</p>
            <p>That night, the daunted Enemy did in the dark ſteale away from <hi>Newbery;</hi> what no tice our friends at <hi>Speen,</hi> had of the marching away of the Enemy, I cannot affirm, for reports are various; though all acknowledge, that they had ſome noiſe thereof: but this I am ſure of, that my Lord of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> had not the leaſt hint of the Enemies retreat, till near day-break in the morning; and his intelligence then, was ſingle and uncertain, from a ſtranger. Yet upon this intimation, his Lordſhip haſtned into the field, to improve opportunity, there the newes was confirmed, that the Enemy was gone indeed. Hereupon our whole body was called together; and ſo ſoon as we had in the field (near the dead bodies both of friends and foes, which lay on the ground) made our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to God, both by praiſe and prayer, according to the preſent affecting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123871:4"/>providences, we marched over the River to <hi>Newbery:</hi> all this while we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther met with, nor heard from our friends at <hi>Speen,</hi> whereupon we hoped that they were in purſuit of the ſcattered flying Enemy. My Lord of <hi>Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> reſted not, till he met with ſome of the Commanders, who had been upon the ſervice at <hi>Speen,</hi> and with them returned to <hi>Newbery,</hi> to conſult about the improvement of the preſent Victory. Theſe particulars, which I knowingly do report, may evidence my Lords forwardneſſe, to husband advantages and opportunities, for the promoting of the publick ſervice. But though my Lord Generals Horſe, and Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> Horſe were gone ſome hours before after the Enemy, yet my Lord <hi>Manchesters</hi> Horſe, (commanded by Lieu. Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi>) we found in the field near <hi>Newbery,</hi> together in a body.</p>
            <p>It would be impertinent, for me here to ſpeak of by-buſineſſes of ſmall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, which common fame hath trumpeted abroad. The taking of the Coaches, with the Men and Horſes attending the perſons in them, was effected by my Lord of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> forwardneſſe, to furniſh Col. <hi>Birch</hi> with a party of Horſe for his aſſiſtance, whereof I am a witneſſe, being uſed as a meſſenger unto my Lord to expedite that work.</p>
            <p>And whether his Lordſhip during our ſtay at <hi>Newbery,</hi> was not as deſirous as any others, in every kinde to ſerve the publick, I refer it to the judgement of them who were daily converſant with him. We having after ſome dayes, full intelligence, that the King was at <hi>Oxford,</hi> there recruting his Army, and hearing alſo, that he intended to fight, ſo ſoon as the additionall forces ſent for, came to him, our Army marched from <hi>Newbery</hi> on Saturday towards <hi>Oxford,</hi> and that night the Head quarter was at <hi>Compton.</hi> Upon Sabbath day the Army marched towards <hi>Blewbery,</hi> and the Head quarter that night was at <hi>Harwell,</hi> and the Army quartered in adjacent Villages, untill this time the Lord <hi>Warriston</hi> and Mr. <hi>Erem</hi> (who came to us at <hi>Baſing,</hi> being ſent from the Committee of both Kingdomes, to aſſiſt the ſervice of the Army by their counſell) can teſtifie what was my Lord of <hi>Manchesters</hi> care and carriage in his place, and unto their teſtimony thus far I might refer them, who are unſatisfied. This day at a Councell of Warre (before theſe our friends left us) it was found impoſſible for us to march with our Carriages beyond <hi>Abbington,</hi> becauſe the wayes, were judged deep and unpaſſable.</p>
            <p>On Monday my Lord with ſome few who attended him, went to <hi>Abbing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> to expreſſe his reſpects to Major Generall <hi>Browne;</hi> and that acquainting himſelf with the ſtate of that place, he might the better know, how to be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to it, and to the Kingdome in it, as occaſion might require. On Tewſday, all our Horſe were called to a Rendevouz upon <hi>Chilton</hi>-plaine (if I forget not the name of the place) where all the chief Commanders of the Army, at a Councel of Warre, concluded our returne unto <hi>Newbery,</hi> the next day. Now
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123871:5"/>becauſe this act (as I heare) is much cenſured (though it was the reſult of the Councel of Warre, and we had alſo the expreſſe approbation of the Committee of both Kingdomes, I will therefore make bold to ſuggeſt the grounds thereof as they were related unto me. 1. That corner of the Countrey (being bare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we came thither) could not afford means of ſubſiſtence for our Army, and we had ſmall hope of receiving ſeaſonably ſufficient ſupplyes elſewhere. 2. By continuing there, we ſhould wholly devoure thoſe proviſions whereby our friends at <hi>Abbington</hi> (being Neighbours) might expect ſome reliefe. 3. Becauſe there was no hope of getting over <hi>Wallingford</hi>-bridge, to fight with the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my on the other ſide the River; and the Enemy might, by making overtures of engaging, and yet deceiving our hopes, have waſted our Army through una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable wants, without ſtriking one blow. 4. And our forces did daily weaken very ſenſibly, through the great ſcarcity of proviſions of all kindes, our Souldiers being under much diſcontent and diſcouragement.</p>
            <p>Theſe reaſons (as I believe) moved our return to <hi>Newbery,</hi> upon Wedneſday, and the ſame night ſome of the Enemies came from <hi>Wallingford,</hi> into the ſame Quarters, from whence we were removed. Upon Thurſday, our Scouts brought newes to <hi>Newbery,</hi> that the Kings whole Army was come over the River, with a parpoſe to relieve <hi>Dennington</hi> Caſtle. And although many amongſt us, gave little or no credit to theſe reports; yet (of my knowledge) my Lord <hi>Manchesters</hi> cautiouſneſſe was ſuch, that hereupon he moved the drawing up of all our Horſe to a Rendevouz the next day, that we might be ready to prevent the relieving of the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>How this his Lordſhips motion took with others I cannot ſay; but that it was diſliked and gainſai'd by Lieu. Gen. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> my ſelf, and many others can teſtifie, who heard him earneſtly diſſwading it, by words to this effect; <hi>My Lord, you Horſe are ſo spent, ſo harraſſed out, by hard duty, that they will fall down under the Riders, if you thus command them, you may have their skin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but you can have no ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although I dare not ſay, that Lieu. Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> did from unfaithfulneſſe to the publick, thus diſſwade the drawing up of our Horſe on Friday. Yet this my ſelf, and many thouſands are moſt confident of, that through this neglect fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the advantage of the Enemy, in relieving the Caſtle, and our diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For our Horſe being (through the ſearcity of proviſions) quartered at a great diſtance from one another, and ſome of our Troops being 10 miles, ſome 12, and ſome 14 miles from <hi>Newbery,</hi> they could not poſſibly (after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larme on Friday in afternoon) come in ſoon enough to prevent the Enemies coming to the Caſtle, much leſſe to fight with the Enemy in a convenient ground, before he came thither: whereas, if our Horſe had been brought together upon Friday (according to my Lord <hi>Manchesters</hi> motion on Thurſday, before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123871:5"/>we might have met the Enemy with a timely and ſucceſſefull reſiſtance (through Gods mercy) at leaſt for the preventing of the Caſtles reliefe.</p>
            <p>But I will look backward, and take up my Relation where I left it. The former intelligence received from the Scouts, and the motion from my Lord made on Thurſday, not being improved, we waited, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, what another day would bring forth: and when certaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtioned tydings came on Friday in the afternoone, that the whole Body of the Enemies Army was on their march towards the Caſtle; then Poſts were diſpatched to the ſeverall Quarters of our Horſe, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to come in early the next morning: but the Enemy having gained the opportunity which we loſt, the Caſtle was relieved, before we were ready to make reſiſtance: yea, the Enemy had placed themſelves in Battalia, in the field betwixt <hi>Dennington</hi>-Caſtle and <hi>Newbery,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our maine Body of Horſe were in any poſture for ſervice. It would not be to my purpoſe in this Relation, to ſpecifie how bravely a party of the Enemies Horſe did aſſault a party of ours, routed them, and did beat them to our Foot, who received the Enemy with much courage, and repulſed them bravely, who took away with them (as we heard after) the dead and wounded bodies of many, who were much eſteemed. Neither doe I intend here to tell, how the ſeverall Commanders, had now diſpoſed of themſelves and their forces. My Lord <hi>Mancheſter</hi> was with Major <hi>Skippon</hi> in the field, where all the skirmidge was that day betwixt us and the Enemy, and they both often and earneſtly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſent for Lieu. Gen. <hi>Cromwels</hi> Horſe, (as I am credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) but they came too late; for before they marched through <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery</hi> towards the Army, the Sunne was ſet, the Enemy was making his retreat out of the field, which mine own eyes and others beheld with much grief of heart. Major Gen. <hi>Crafford</hi> (who is knowne to be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently forward to engage) though his command was over the Foot, yet upon my Lord of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> cummand, himſelfe alſo being moved in the approach of the daring Enemy, did with 9 or 10 Troops (ſome or moſt whereof he rallied amongſt them formerly routed) charge a body of the Enemies Horſe, and cauſed them to give ground. By this it may be gueſſed what good ſervice might have been done, if more Horſe had been at hand. That night, I hearing many accuſations charged upon the Horſe which came not in, I made bold for mine owne ſatisfaction,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123871:6"/>to enquire (of a valiant Commander my worthy friend) the reaſons wherefore thoſe Horſe kept at ſuch a diſtance from ſervice that day, from whom Ireceived theſe. 1. Becauſe there was not field room for our whole Body to ſerve in. 2. Becauſe (if they had come in) in that ground, they ſhould have been expoſed to the Cannon, playing from the Caſtle, which would in probability, either have broken, or diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their ſeverall Bodies before they could engage. You ſee, that I am deſirous in my Narration, to give all men their right, and to keep off groundleſſe cenſures. And here I wiſh, that it may ſtill be impartially conſidered, whether yet it appear by this true relation, that the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> was more averſe to the Kingdoms ſervice, then other men, when either neceſſity or opportunity did require it.</p>
            <p>The Caſtle being relieved, and the Enemy retreated, our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders in chiefe, upon conſultation reſolved that night to ſend forth about 4000 Horſe with ſome Foot, to fall upon the Enemies Rear, ſo ſoon as the Moon did ariſe, hoping by this means to regain what we had loſt the day before: but the Enemy continuing all night in a full body, that deſigne was diſappointed.</p>
            <p>In the morning our whole Army was drawne forth, with intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and expoctation to fight with the Enemy, before his removall out of our reach. This being noiſed, my ſelf, with other Miniſters who atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Campe, did our duty by prayer and exhortation, to prepare them for the expected battell. But when our Commanders had viewed the ſtrength and poſture of the Kings Army, and the advantage of ground which they had gained, together with the dangerouſneſſe of the paſſages to the Enemy (being both near <hi>Dennington</hi> Caſtle, and through Lanes) they with one minde at a Councell of War, judged it unſafe to engage. What paſſed in conference at the Councel of War, I know not, neither did I judge it meet for me to enquire after thoſe matters: But this I profeſſe, that I heard not any, either Officer, or other, to blame my Lord of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> as more backward at that Councel of Want then others, to engage with the withdrawing Enemy. Afterwards, while the Army continued at <hi>Newbery,</hi> and the parts adjacent, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member nothing of moment to be reported, but this one thing, (which if not rightly underſtood, may occaſion miſtakes, no prejudice) that whereas 3 Regiments of my Lords Foot, were ordered to march unto <hi>Baſing,</hi> to aſſiſt the Horſe in the ſervice there, they were commanded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123871:6"/>(when on their march) to returne back, according to the counſell of Sir <hi>W. Waller</hi> and Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwel</hi> (as they were going with my Lord in his Coach to <hi>Aldermarſton</hi>) upon theſe grounds, as I was informed. 1. Becauſe there would not in likelihood be any need of that ſtrength there at that time. 2. Becauſe their comming thither would ſtraighten the Quarters of thoſe who were already there, and conſequently, make their continuance more uncomfortable. When upon an Alarm, that the Kings whole Army, was on their march to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Baſing-houſe;</hi> it was ordered, that our Forces ſhould remove from <hi>Newbery</hi> to joyne with our Horſe ſent to <hi>Baſing</hi> before. Now I was neceſſitated through bodily diſtempers, to withdraw from the Campe, and therefore cannot from obſervation ſpeak of the paſſages afterwards. But I have been told againe and againe, that the calling off of our Horſe and Foot, from <hi>Baſing,</hi> was from the order of a Councell of War, no man deſerting; and alſo, that no man was more forward in giving his vote, for that Order, then Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Cromwel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſumme of what I have to ſay, concerning the chiefe Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences in our Weſterne expedition; wherein, though we had not ſuch happy ſucceſſe, as was deſired and expected, yet therein, thoſe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged much of Gods goodneſſe, who did moſt exactly obſerve his providences in our motions and adventures. Herein I have faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, according to my obſervation and beſt intelligence, repreſented things, with ſpeciall references to my much Honoured Lord, becauſe through miſreports, and misbeliefe, his Lordſhip is rendred to the world, under the black clowd, of ſad reproaches. His Honour I confeſſe, is very deare unto me, and the heavy cenſures with which many doe loade and wound his eſtimation amonſt men, doe much afflict me: yet (I bleſſe God) the cauſe, wherewith his Lordſhip hath been truſted, and wherein he hath ſucceſſefully appeared, is much more deate and pretions, yea (if I know mine own heart) I would deſert his Lordſhip, and my ſelf alſo, deſerting that glorious cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt. I well remember, thoſe words, <hi>Job.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Will ye speake. wiekedly for God, and talke deceitfully for him?</hi> And therefore I am awed with the feare of God, while I am pleading for man. Yet this I doe moſt ſeriouſly profeſſe, as in the preſence of the heart-ſearching Majeſtie, that I know no cauſe, wherefore I ſhould once queſtion his Lordſhips ſidelity to the cauſe of Reformation, and that ſervice of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123871:7"/>the Kingdome, wherin he hath been proſperouſly imployed. But as the matter of his Accuſation is to me moſt ſtrange and unexpected; ſo the manner of managing it, by many, who are accounted not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious but eminently pious, is to me and many, a matter of much wonder: For ſhould not thoſe who have received favours from my Lord of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and have ſolemnely profeſſed truth and ſtrength of reſpects to his Lordſhip, rather have ſignified in private their ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his faithfulneſſe (if they apprehended cauſe) then proclaime to the world, offences, whereof he never heard? Might not his known meekneſſe and ſweetneſſe of diſpoſition, have encouraged them, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this office of faithfulneſſe, who often had the opportunity of ſecrecie to have performed it? Would not ſuch a courſe rather have anſwered that rule of our Saviour: If thy brother offend, goe and tell him his fault, between thee and him alone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then to divulge (I will ſay no more) in a publick way, thoſe things wherof his own heart never ſuſpected himſelf to be ſuſpected? What Chriſtians, yea what men doe not looke for ſuch friendſhip, ſuch ingenuity, from them who converſe with them daily, and ordinarily come to eate meate at their tables? And had the prejudice of the publick long been feared, through the apprehenſion of any ill principles poſſeſſing the Earle of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> breaſt, why was not this ſooner ſuggeſted, for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of publick prejudice?</p>
            <p>I will not dare to gueſſe either at the grounds, or ends of that which now is broken forth, but ſhall leave ſecrets unto the Lord, who in his own time will make the counſels of all hearts manifeſt, and bring to light the deeds, the deſignes of darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Neither doe I thus expoſtulate, as yeelding to the truth of the matters, which are commonly charged upon him: for I have many reaſons to believe the contrary, ſome whereof, I ſhall briefely mention.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhips former actions and adventures for the publick, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him in the opinion of the godly party in the Kingdome, as a true, truſty Patriot, both to Church and Common-wealth; and truly, I am ignorant, what ſhould cauſe people to alter that opinion, though I have of late, had more opportunities to diſcover him, then other men.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip hath often, in the hearing of many witneſſes, thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed himſelfe ſolemnely, <hi>I could contentedly part with halft my
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123871:7"/>eſtate, upon condition the diſcipline of Chriſt was eſtabliſhed, and a good Miniſtry ſetled in every Congregation of the Kingdome, yea with thoſe couditions, how gladly could I betake my ſelfe unto a Country life, and leave all other contentments in the world.</hi> Oh how frequent, how conſtant have his breathings beene after peace, with the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of that Reformation which is hopefully begun. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a thing incredible to them who know him, that he ſhould take any courſe, to continue the Civill (or rather uncivill) warres of the Kingdome, which doe continue and increaſe confuſions. I know no man, who attends the Campe, leſſe ſelf-ſeeking, and more deſirous to iſſue the Warres, in a comfortable Peace, then my Lord of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is to my ſelfe, an evidence of my Lords innocency, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of what is laid to his charge; that when friends had ſuggeſted to him by Letters, Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwels</hi> purpoſe to accuſe him (as was gathered from intimations looking that way) he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely proteſted, that his integrity was ſuch, that he could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any ſuch matter: Yea though he did caſt about in his own thoughts, what matter of juſt exception might be laid in againſt him (for he was farre from expecting falſe accuſations) he profeſſed ſeriouſly, he could not imagin what it might be; except it were ſome old com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, in reference to Major Generall <hi>Crafford,</hi> and ſome late eſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from Liev. Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> ſince his heates expreſſed at <hi>Lincolne,</hi> which gave occaſion of juſt offence.</p>
            <p>And when upon his comming to <hi>London,</hi> his Lordſhip underſtood in generals, that unfaithfulneſſe, and unwillingneſſe to improve oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities and counſels for the publick good, againſt the common Enemy, was laid to his charge, by Liev. Gen. <hi>Cromwell;</hi> this was his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips anſwer: <hi>I pray God forgive him, for he knowes in his conſcience, that he hath wronged me, in ſpeaking untruly.</hi> And theſe words falling from a friend, <hi>How much will your Lordſhip ſuffer in your honour, by meanes of this asperſion?</hi> His Lordſhip returned this reply, <hi>My defence is from God, who ſaveth the upright in heart.</hi> Theſe things, which of my credit are truths (unto which many more might truly be added) I leave to the conſideration of the ingenious, calme, unbyaſſed Chriſtian, how farre they may at leaſt perſwade the ſuſpenſion of cenſures and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, till my Lord hath vindicated himſelf from his accuſations.</p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid. There is no ſmoke, but it argues ſome fire. And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123871:8"/>the reports of people, yea of good people, againſt my Lord of <hi>Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> are ſo common, that doubtleſſe all is not right.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but Gods hand is in my Lords ſufferings of this kinde, who hath learned to juſtifie God when injured by men. He hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed his deſire to know Gods meaning in the Rod, and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed his willingneſſe to ſee, that he might reforme, whatſoever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eſpy blame-worthy in his courſe. But the opinion and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the multitude, is no good argument to prove him guilty in that kinde and meaſure, as charged. It is an evill to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that people are ſo apt, with credulity to take up evill reports againſt their Brethren. Beſides, the world underſtands, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perſons acted by principles oppoſite to one another, are yet both violently contrary to the wayes of my Lord of <hi>Manchester:</hi> from hence the duſt may be raiſed and continued, which for the preſent doth darken his repuration, which was wont to ſhine forth more brightly, and which God (I hope) in his good time will cleare againe.</p>
            <p>I might here take occaſion, to mention many ſtrange palpable untruths, ſtanderouſly raiſed and ſpread, yea, conveyed by Letters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, to blaſt the credit of them, who deſire to walk with God: and no reaſon here can be imagined, but their difference in indgement and practice from them, in ſome matters of Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. But that Scripture doth check me. <hi>Tell it not in Gath, and publiſh it not in Ask<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lon, lest the uncircumciſed triumph.</hi> The Lord heale our breaches, reconcile our differences, and knit our hearts together in more ſtrong brotherly love through Chriſt.</p>
            <p>My ſelfe expects ſevere cenſure from many people for this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which (in the judgement of many worthy godly friends) I had a call to diſcharge: but I hope the ſincerity of my heart through Gods grace will ſupport me under ſuch burthens, if they ſhall be caſt upon me.</p>
            <p>If my faultineſſe ſhall be diſcovered, the Lord I truſt will ſo farre preſerve me, that I ſhall not adde ſtubbornneſſe to weakneſſe. And if any ſhall paſſionately and unchriſtianly throw ſtones at me, and caſt dirt in my face, I hope, that my God will make me able to pity them, and to pray for them, and to learn more humility and circumſpection in my converſation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:123871:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
